V. A. Allen and Foster Fanning Potter Physicians' Account Books
V. A. Allen and Foster Fanning Potter Physicians' Account Books
1839-1890
Allen, V. A.
2 linear ft. (14 volumes)
Collection of highly detailed medical account books kept by general practitioner V. A. [Vine A.] Allen and later by his successor Dr. Foster Fanning Potter of the village of Cleveland in Constantia township, Oswego County, New York.
4124022
Biographical History
V. A. (Vine A.) Allen graduated from Castleton Medical College in 1833. As of 1877 he was a physician in Cleveland village, along with a D. T. Whyborn who was for a time his partner. He also served as postmaster for the village.
Dr. Foster Fanning Potter graduated from University Medical College in 1880. His father Asher Smith Potter (1805-1881) was one of the first village officers, being a trustee when the village was incorporated in 1857, and operated a tavern and later a store in Cleveland village. In addition to his medical work Dr. Potter was postmaster for the village of Constantia and served on the Board of Education for the Cleveland Union Free School, the only incorporated educational institution in Constantia.
Sources:
Fifty-Ninth Announcement of Castleton Medical College for the Annual Session 1860 with a Catalogue of the Alumni, 1860, p. 6
General Alumni Catalogue of New York University, 1833-1907: Medical Alumni, 1908, p. 280
History of Oswego County, New York, 1877, p. 291
Landmarks of Oswego County New York, 1895, pp. 283, 291, 497, 504, 508
Record of Appointment of Postmasters, 1832-Sept. 30, 1971, National Archives and Records Administration
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The V. A. Allen and Foster Fanning Potter Physicians' Account Books consists of fourteen volumes detailing treatment of a wide range of medical ailments and conditions, including dates, fees, payments (including in-kind), medicines prescribed (unguents, ointments, liniments, drops, pills, etc.). Among their patients were workers at the American Glass Company and Union Glass Company, both of which are repeatedly credited with paying their employees' medical bills.
Entries of particular interest include a half a page of details regarding an operation on a hydrocephalic child (1889). At least one of the volumes includes Dr. Allen's supply orders: glassware, opium, morphine, spices, alcohol, etc. The final volume includes not only Dr. Potter's medical accounts but also records the sale of various "drugstore" materials such as tobacco, candy, soap, and so on.
Arrangement of the Collection
Chronological. Volume numbers have been assigned for each of identification.
Related Material
has several collections of physicians' day books. Please to locate additional items of interest.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Science and medicine; Allen, V. A. (Vine A.); Potter, Foster Fanning.; Medicine -- Practice -- Accounting.; Physicians -- New York (State); Cleveland (N.Y.) -- History -- 19th century.; Constantia (N.Y.: Town) -- History -- 19th century.; Oswego County (N.Y.) -- History -- 19th century.; Account books.; Pharmacists.; Physicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2014.
Inventory
- Account books
  - [Volume 1], 1839-1842 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 2], 1848-1850 (Oversize 2)
  - [Volume 3], 1851-1855 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 4], 1854-1859 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 5], 1860-1864 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 6], 1861-1863 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 7], 1868-1870 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 8], 1871-1875 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 9], 1875-1881 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 10], 1882-1885 (Oversize 2)
  - [Volume 11], 1881-1890 (Oversize 3)
  - [Volume 12], 1881-1890 (Oversize 3)
  - [Volume 13], 1889-1890 (Oversize 1)
  - [Volume 14], 1889-1890 (Oversize 1)